<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>A sketch of the background to this project</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Before the Tromsø project</title>

      <p>Around 1980, Lauri Karttunen, Ron Kaplan and Martin Kay found ways of
      turning generative rewriting rules into finite-state automata. In 1983,
      Kimmo Koskenniemi defended his doctoral dissertation, where he was able
      to compile such automata for the grammar of a heavily inflecting
      language, Finnish. During the eighties, rule sets for several languages
      were made, but the process of writing automata by hand was a very
      tedious one. Towards the end of the decade, researchers at Xerox were
      able to make a machine compiler (twolc for Koskenniemi's two-level
      morphophonological rules, and later lexc for the lexicon and and xfst
      for the whole parser). The Xerox twolc compiler became the cornerstone
      of much work, a.o. for the spellchecking programs made for the Nordic
      languages by the Helsinki-based company Lingsoft.</p>

      <p>In 1993, Pekka Sammallahti got a grant to spend 6 months writing the
      prototype for the first Sámi parser, as a guest researcher at the Nordic
      Sámi Institute in Guovdageaidnu. It covered the basic morphophonology
      and inflection for the nouns, adjectives and verbs of Northern Sámi. The
      work was done on Xerox tools lexc and twolc for Macintosh, and included
      discussions with Kimmo Koskenniemi and Lauri Karttunen. Sammallahti's
      parser was made as a quasi-morphematic model, with simple stems, but a
      rich system of sublexica adding diacritical marks that triggered the
      morphophonological processes found for different Sámi stem classes.</p>

      <p>In 1998, Sjur Moshagen and Trond Trosterud found themselves in an
      unstable job marked, sharing and interest for Southern Sámi, stemming
      from the days of the Corpus project for small Uralic languages, which
      they had initiated back in 1994. Moshagen then worked at Lingsoft, and
      Trosterud was looking for ways of doing linguistics in Tromsø. They
      decided to write a Southern Sámi parser. Unaware of Sammallahti's work
      on Northern Sámi, they made a parser with different architecture: They
      encoded as much morphophonological information as possible in the stems,
      and in exchange got a very simple set of sublexica. They did not have
      access to a dictionary, confined their work to the inflection of
      non-compounded nouns.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Tromsø projects</title>

      <p>After several attempts, Trosterud in 2000 managed to get a 3-year NFR
      grant for making a Northern Sámi parser. During the preparatory work he
      became aware of Sammallahti's parser, and luckily enough, Sammallahti
      offered the parser source code and his dictionary as a starting point
      for the parser project. In this way, the project got a flying start, and
      duplicate work was avoided. Due to the extra time provided by
      Sammallahti's basic work, Trosterud was able to write a Lule Sámi
      parser, and also continue the work on parts of the Southern Sámi parser
      (including it into the common infrastructure, and adding support for
      closed parts of speech).</p>

      <p>In 2004, the University of Tromsø got a second 3-year grant, as a
      part of the NFR KUNSTI project, with funding for 2 linguists and 1/2
      programmer, in order to make a morphological disambiguator for Northern
      Sámi, and as a control exercise, one for Lule Sámi as well. This project
      is now half-way, and it is documented on these pages.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sámi localisation</title>

      <p>There has been various attempts at ensuring the Sámi languages
      localisation solutions (solutions for getting the Sámi letters right, on
      screen and printer, for getting good keyboard layouts, sorting
      algorithms, date-and-time formats, etc.). In this context, we may state
      that all the Sámi languages are represented in the Unicode standard.
      Unicode support is not enough, but because of the work of a small group
      of enthusiasts (especially Per Edvard Klemetsen and Audun Lona for
      Windows, Michael Everson and Michal Aase for Macintosh and Børre Gaup
      and Regnor Jernsletten for Linux), Northern Sámi is now the smallest
      language in the world with localisation support, out-of-the-box, for all
      the three OS-s. Work on Sámi language technology now is based upon
      Unicode.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Planning the spell-checker program</title>

      <p>As spellchecking programs for other languages became better, several
      Sámis saw the increased need for such programs for Sámi. In 2002, Per
      Edvard Klemetsen contacted Trond Trosterud in order to get a grip of
      what it would take to make a Sámi spellchecker. Trosterud put Klemetsen
      and Moshagen in contact with each other, as Moshagen, together with all
      his collegues, had just been laid off from his job as the leader of
      Lingsoft's dictionary division. Moshagen wrote the pilot project for a
      Sámi spellchecker program. Then, Klemetsen did a very good job when
      raising funds for the project. Although somewhat reduced (from initial
      19 MNOK to the actual 11.3 MNOK), the project was able to launch at the
      end of 2004, with a 3-year schedule.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The present projects, and beyond</title>

      <p>The main focus at present is on finishing the twin projects:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>For the university project, to finish the disambiguator and make a
        website with tagged corpora and a graphical user interface for
        research use</li>

        <li>For the Divvun project, to deliver spell checkers for Northern and
        Lule Sámi</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Beyond that there are several obvious next steps:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>To extend the work to more languages <ol>
            <li>The obvious first candidate is Southern Sámi, for which there
            already is a partial parser ready</li>

            <li>There are 3 more Sámi languages, working with them would be a
            good way of involving linguists from Finland and Russla</li>

            <li>With the ready-made infrastructure, one obvious strategy is to
            extend it to other minority languages, as has already been done
            for Komi and Greenlandic</li>
          </ol></li>

        <li>To work on lexicography and language technology<ol>
            <li>... by making intelligent dictionaries</li>

            <li>... by using parallel corpora as termbases</li>

            <li>... by </li>
          </ol></li>

        <li>To make pedagogical programs</li>

        <li>To make grammar checkers</li>
      </ol>

      <p>The University of Tromsø will initiate a program in Sámi lexicography
      and language technology, thereby contributing to fulfulling these goals.
      </p>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>