<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Text corpus legalese</title>

    <subtitle>Text licensing, end users, and other contracts</subtitle>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>

    <abstract>This page contains an overview of the contracts required to
    build a usable corpus, both seen from the perspective of the collector,
    the administrator of the collection, and the end user.
    The contracts are translations of the documents at the <a
    href="http://www.csc.fi/suomi/info/index.phtml.en">Finnish IT center for
    science</a> for their <a
    href="http://www.csc.fi/kielipankki/index.phtml.sv">Text bank</a>.</abstract>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>The Helsinki model, and template contracts</title>

      <p>We have decided to use the contracts from Helsinki university, as
      they have a reasonable history in active use in a national text bank
      project, and provides for easy division of labor as well as clear
      separation of responsibilities between Sámediggi and the University of
      Tromsø.</p>

      <p>The Helsinki originals and their Norwegian translations are available
      for free reuse by others that find them useful, but please note that the
      Norwegian translation is not yet ready. Also, the translation has
      brought forward a few unclear points in the Finnish originals that
      should be clarified.</p>

      <p>Finally, we have an example from the University of Oslo as a
      comparison.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Background</title>

        <fixme author="SNM">Add a background section (or document) with a
        short explanation of the model used in Helsinki.</fixme>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Original contracts</title>

        <p>The Helsinki University license contract from the Linguistic
        Department consists of four parts:</p>

        <ol>
          <li>First part original <a href="/static_files/hki-ex-1.tex">LaTeX</a>, <a href="/static_files/hki-ex-1.pdf">pdf</a></li>

          <li>Second part original <a href="/static_files/hki-ex-2.tex">LaTeX</a>, <a href="/static_files/hki-ex-2.pdf">pdf</a></li>

          <li>Third part original <a href="/static_files/hki-ex-3.tex">LaTeX</a>, <a href="/static_files/hki-ex-3.pdf">pdf</a></li>

          <li>The fourth part is not yet available</li>
        </ol>

        <p>There is also a supporting <a href="/static_files/man.sty">style
        specification</a> for the LaTeX originals.</p>

        <p>The above version of the 1. Helsinki contract is missing §3.8
        (present in earlier paper versions), and needs to be reinserted. What
        looks like §3.8 corresponds to §3.9 in the earlier version.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Norwegian translations</title>

        <ol>
          <li><a href="hki-contract-example.html">First part</a></li>
          <li><a href="hki-contract-example-2.html">Second part</a></li>
          <li><a href="hki-contract-example-3.html">Third part</a></li>

          <li>The fourth part is not yet available</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Sámediggi contracts</title>

      <p>The translations above of the Helsinki contracts will be the basis
      for our own contracts. They are not yet finished, as the main work now
      is focusing on getting the translations in shape. The existing drafts
      are:</p>

      <ol>
        <li><a href="sd-contract.html">First part</a></li>

        <li><a href="sd-contract-part-2.html">Second part</a></li>

        <li><a href="sd-contract-part-3.html">Third part</a></li>

        <li>Fourth part not yet available</li>
      </ol>

      <p>These translations will be sent to a lawyer for thorough
      checking.</p>

      <note>Should we add links to XML versions of our translations?</note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Oslo contracts</title>

      <p>For comparison, the contract from the University of Oslo, Department
      of Linguistics and Scandinavian Studies, with the corresponding end user
      license:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>The <a href="oslo-standard-contract.html">text licensing
        contract</a> (corresponds to contract 1 and 2 in the Helsinki
        model)</li>

        <li>The <a href="http://www.hf.uio.no/tekstlab/innsyn/skjema.html">end
        user contract</a>, corresponding to contract 3 and 4 below</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>