<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="nb">
  <header>
    <title>Press release, 29.5.2007</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Press release</title>

      <p>Date: 29.5.2007<br /> Contact person: Project leader Sjur
      Nørstebø Moshagen, phone +358 50 56 34 319</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>PRM: Beta version of Sámi Proofing Tools</title>

      <p>the Sámi Parliament's Divvun project is today releasing the first
      publicly available version of Sámi proofing tools for the Microsoft
      Office suite. The suite contains among others the applications Word,
      Outlook, PowerPoint and Excel.</p>

      <p>The Sámi proofing tools contain spell checkers for North Sámi and Lule
      Sámi, and an automatic hyphenator for North Sámi.
      Hyphenation for Lule Sámi will come later this year. All tools are free, 
      included the final version, and all source code for the tools made by the
      Sámi Parliament are freely available.</p>

      <p>The tools launched today are not the final ones, but a so-called beta
      version, a version who should be void of any serious technical and other
      errors, but who still is not developed and tested.
      The goal by releasing this beta version is to get important feedback 
      when it comes to missing words, eventual technical problems, and other
      possible weaknesses, so that they may be corrected before the final
      release at the end of the year.</p>

      <p>The proofing tools being released are tools for MS
      Office for Windows and Mac. Tools for InDesign and OpenOffice.org will
      be released at a later date. OpenOffice.org is a free alternative to
      Microsoft Office, and is also available for Linux. Updates to the proofing
      tools will be published at regular intervals.</p>

      <p>The tools are available at <a href="http://www.divvun.no/"
      >www.divvun.no</a>, and can be downloaded by all interested parties.
      Copies of the tools may also be downloaded from <a
      href="http://www.sametinget.no/">the Sámi Parliaments homepage</a>.</p>

      <p>The Divvun project is run by the Norwegian Sámi Parliament, and is
      financed by the Sámi Parliament, the Ministry of labour and social
      inclusion, the Ministry of Culture and Church affairs, the Ministry of
      Education and Research, and Nordplus Sprog. The project
      cooperates closely with <a href="http://giellatekno.uit.no/"
      >the Sámi language technology centre at the University of
      Tromsø</a>. Integration with MS
      Office is delivered by <a href="http://www.polderland.nl/">Polderland
      Language &amp; Speech Technology bv</a>.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
