<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Outsourcing</title>

    <subtitle>Requirements specification for project tasks to be
    outsourced</subtitle>

    <version>0.1</version>

    <type>Internal draft</type>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjurnm@mac.com" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>

    <abstract>This document describes the exact requirements for each
    component and each task within the outsourced part of the project. It
    should preferably be tied to a tool for generating test cases to verify
    the conformance with the specifications of each component, but as the tool
    is not yet in place, it will for the time being be free form. For the same
    reason, the content is rather rudimentary.</abstract>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Source files</title>

      <p>The data provided by the Divvun project is a computational linguistic
      model built using Xerox finite state tools, and thus the source files
      are in the formats supported by Xerox. More specifically, the source
      files are of the following types, extensively described in Beesley &amp;
      Karttunen 2003:</p>

      <dl>
        <dt>twolc</dt>

        <dd>morphophonological descriptions, accounting for phenomenas such as
        consonant gradation, vowel shortening, monophtongization, etc.</dd>

        <dt>lexc</dt>

        <dd>covers both morphological processes such as compounding,
        derivation and inflection, as well as the complete lexicon</dd>
      </dl>

      <p>The cooperating companies are expected to be able to take these
      formats directly as their input, or make scripts that will convert from
      the Xerox formats to the companies internal formats without loss or
      change of linguistic coverage.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Technical specification of deliverables</title>

      <p>As well as acceptance criteria for the deliverables.</p>
    </section>

    
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>