<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Outsourcing — selection criterias</title>

    <subtitle>A precise description of the criteria used for selecting
    vendors</subtitle>

    <version major="2" minor="0">Revised version after the board
    meeting</version>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>This document is written in conformance with the guidelines from the
      Norwegian ministry of trade and industry (Nærings- og
      handelsdepartementet, NHD) (see «Veileder», link on the overview
      page).</p>

      <p>The purpose of the selection criteria is to select the economically
      most appealling offer. The main criterion is price, but also indirect
      costs and longer term costs will influence the decision.</p>

      <p>The selection criteria as well as the weighting have been approved by
      the project board.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selection criteria</title>

      <p>The selected offer is the economically most attractive one. That
      implies an evaluation of price and the following criteria:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Technical compatibility with our existing linguistic resources and
        language technology.</li>

        <li>Willingness to license tools to compile the binary lexicon for the
        proofing tools to Sámediggi and the project group, such that
        linguistic, non-technical updates can be delivered to end users
        without involvement from the cooperating companies).</li>

        <li>The total cost in a longer perspective. This includes the price
        for this project, and the costs for maintenance updates, combined with
        the costs for the Sámi Parliament for the same maintenance.</li>

        <li>Quality, functionality and user friendliness. Quality and user
        evaluation of corresponding tools for other languages. In the case of
        the InDesign hyphenator, it is essential that a company can provide a
        documented capability to develop high-quality hyphenation modules,
        benefitting from our linguistic work and tools. In the case of
        proofing tools for MS Office, it is important that the estimated
        quality of the end user products is high enough for our end users, to
        reduce the risk of extra work and higher costs later on in the
        project.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>The exact documentation needed to support a decision based on these
      criteria is specified in the main public tender document.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The final word</title>

      <p>The winning company is the one that, after a total evaluation of
      price and quality criteria, gives the best offer. Price will be
      important. The decision is made by the project board.</p>
    </section>

    
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>
