<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
   <header>
      <title>InDesign Proofing Tools Documentation</title>
   </header>
   <body>
      <p>The Divvun tools for InDesign has earlier only supported InDesign CS3 due to lack of support for newer versions
      of InDesign from our subcontractor. But with the release of CS5.5, InDesign supports the same proofing tools as
      OpenOffice, which Divvun has supported in a Beta version for many years. The Divvun group will thus start using
      the OpenOffice/LibreOffice tools for InDesign. This also means that we will be able to support InDesign running on
      Windows.</p>
      <p>Below you will find installation instructions for both InDesign CS3 and InDesign CS5.5. CS4 and CS5 are not
      supported, and will never be. Support for CS6 is probably the same as for CS5.5, but has not yet been tested or
      documented.</p>
      <section>
         <title>InDesign CS3</title>
         <p>The InDesign CS3 proofing tools components are built on the same technology and architecture as the proofing
         tools for MS Office. There is a <a href="http://divvun.no/doc/proof/hyph/MSOff/index.html">separate page</a> documenting how
         the hyphenation works.</p>
         <p>Proofing tools for InDesign CS3 are provided for both North, Lule and South Sámi. They work only with the
         Macintosh version of InDesign. They require InDesign CS3.</p>
         <section>
            <title>Download and installation</title>
            <p>The latest version is always available here: <a
            href="http://divvun.no/static_files/indesign-divvuntools.dmg">divvun.no/static_files/indesign-divvuntools.dmg</a>.</p>
            <ol>
               <li>After download, open the dmg file. You should see the following window (or something close to
               it):<br/><img alt="divvun-DMG" src="images/divvun-dmg-cs3.png"/></li>
               <li>Open the installation package (double-click it), and follow the instructions:<br/><img
               alt="Divvun installer" src="images/divvun-installer-cs3.png"/></li>
               <li>Quit and restart InDesign if it was running. That's it!</li>
            </ol>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>Upgrading from an earlier version</title>
            <p>Just install atop an existing installation by following the instructions above.</p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>Deinstallation/removal</title>
            <p>Manually move the following files and folder to the thrash:</p>
            <source>In the folder: /Applications/Adobe InDesign CS3/Plug-Ins/

delete the following files:

PldHypSamiLule.InDesignPlugin
PldHypSamiNorthern.InDesignPlugin
PldHypSamiSouthern.InDesignPlugin
PldSplSamiLule.InDesignPlugin
PldSplSamiNorthern.InDesignPlugin
PldSplSamiSouthern.InDesignPlugin

In the folder: /Applications/Adobe InDesign CS3/Plug-Ins/Dictionaries/

delete the following folder and all its contents:

Polderland</source>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>Technical requirements</title>
            <p>The InDesign proofing tools modules have the following requirements:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>InDesign CS3</li>
               <li>MacOS X 10.4.8 or newer</li>
            </ul>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>InDesign CS5.5</title>
         <note>The InDesign CS5.5 support is in beta stage at the moment. There are some issues with the speller, and
         the hyphenator is known to be bad at hyphenating compounds. Hyphenation is presently only available for North
         Sámi. A beta release is planned for May 1.</note>
         <section>
            <title>MacOSX</title>
            <p>Follow these instructions:</p>
            <ol>
               <li>Download the <a href="http://divvun.no/static_files/indesign-divvuntools.dmg">latest InDesing
               installer - a dmg file</a></li>
               <li>After download, open the dmg file. You should see the following window (or something close to
               it):<br/><img alt="divvun-DMG" src="images/divvun-dmg-cs55.png"/></li>
               <li>Open the installation package (double-click it), and follow the instructions:<br/><img
               alt="Divvun installer" src="images/divvun-installer-cs55.png"/></li>
               <li>Quit and restart InDesign if it was running. That's it!</li>
            </ol>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>Windows</title>
            <p>For the time being, only manual install is available for Windows users. To install Divvun for InDesign
            CS5.5, follow these steps:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>download the <a href="http://divvun.no/static_files/smi.zip">Hunspell package</a></li>
               <li>double click the zip file you just downloaded</li>
               <li>follow <a
               href="http://blogs.adobe.com/typblography/2011/11/how-to-enable-more-languages-in-indesign-cs5-5.html">these
               instructions</a> with the following modifications/additions:<ul>
                     <li>use the <code>*.aff</code> and <code>*.dic</code> files from the zip file obtained above</li>
                     <li>you do not need to add the country code, only the ISO 639 language code is enough. That is:
                     <code>se</code> for North Sámi, <code>smj</code> for Lule Sámi, and <code>sma</code> for South
                     Sámi. The aff and dic files are already named like this, just use the same names for their
                     folders.</li>
                     <li>make sure the files have correct owner, group and permissions. It should be
                     <code>root:admin</code>, and <code>read-only</code> for all.</li>
                  </ul></li>
            </ul>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>Deinstallation (both MacOSX and Windows)</title>
            <p>Only manual deinstallation is available for the time being. Follow the instructions <a
            href="http://blogs.adobe.com/typblography/2011/11/how-to-enable-more-languages-in-indesign-cs5-5.html">here</a>,
            at the end of the section entitled "Method Two: Hunspell dictionary". Automated deinstallation will be
            provided at a later point.</p>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Known issues</title>
         <p>There is <a href="KnownIssuesForIndesignCS3.html">a separate page with FAQ, known issues, and suggestions for
         work-arounds</a>.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Usage</title>
         <p>Proofing for Sámi works exactly as for any other language. Follow the InDesign instructions for turning on
         automatic hyphenation and continuous spell checking, and select one of the languages <code>Sami:
         Northern</code>, <code>Sami: Lule</code> or <code>Sami: Sout</code> (for CS3) / <code>Northern Sámi</code>,
         <code>Lule Sámi</code> or <code>South Sámi</code> (for CS5.5) in the language list. The text will reflow, with
         hyphens automatically inserted where needed, and misspellings will be marked with a red underline.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Feedback</title>
         <p>We appreciate any feedback on the proofing tools. Feedback can be sent via e-mail to one of the following
         addresses:</p>
         <ul>
            <li><a href="mailto:feedback@divvun.no">feedback@divvun.no</a></li>
            <li><a href="mailto:feedback@divvun.no">feedback@divvun.no</a></li>
         </ul>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>
