<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
    <header>
        <title>Text-to-speech</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <note label="News!">North Sámi text-to-speech released
        6.5.2015!</note>

        <p><a href="/index.html">Divvun</a> and <a
        href="http://sametinget.no">the Norwegian Sámi Parliament</a> has
        developed a North Sámi speech synthesis system in cooperation with <a
        href="http://www.acapela-group.com/">Acapela</a>. Speech syntehsis, or
        text-to-speech (TTS), allows the computer to transform text to
        natural speech in many applications. By using a screen reader
        (must be installed separately) all text on the screen can be read aloud.
        There are two Sámi voices, one female voice ("Elle") and one male voice
        ("Biera").
        </p>

        <p>The North Sámi text-to-speech system is available in two versions
        for end users:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><strong>North Sámi Infovox 4 for Windows</strong></li>
            <li><strong>North Sámi iVox for OS X</strong></li>
        </ul>

        <p>North Sámi Infovox (for Windows) is delivered on a USB dongle, which
        can be ordered free of charge from the Norwegian Sámi Parliament or <a
        href="mailto:feedback@divvun.no">from the Divvun group at UiT
        (feedback@divvun.no)</a>. The USB dongle is for one user only, but can
        be removed from the computer after installation. The USB dongle makes it
        possible to use the North Sámi speech syntheis on other computers than
        one's own, by bringing it along and plug it into a different computer
        and then starting the speech synthesis application directly from the
        USB dongle without installing anything. More detailed instructions can
        be found <a href="infovox4.en.pdf">here</a>.</p>

        <p>iVox for OS X can be downloaded and installed free of charge from
        <a href="https://www.assistiveware.com/support/infovox-ivox/software"
        >here</a>. To activate and put the North Sámi voices to use one needs an
        activation code. This code can be had free of charge by contacting the
        <a href="mailto:feedback@divvun.no">Divvun group at
        UiT (feedback@divvun.no)</a>. Instructions for installation and use
        can be found <a class="fork"
        href="http://download.assistiveware.com/ivox/files/Infovox%20iVox%20User%20Manual%20Swedish%204.1.pdf"
        >here (in Swedish)</a> and <a class="fork"
        href="http://download.assistiveware.com/ivox/files/Infovox%20iVox%20User%20Manual%204.0.1.pdf"
        >here (in English)</a>.
        </p>

        <p>Acapela has <a class="fork" href="http://www.acapela-group.com/">a demo page</a> where you can try the North Sámi
        voices on a text of your own.
        </p>

        <p>Is it possible to adapt the voices to your own needs. There are
        instructions in the Acapela <a href="Manual_Sami.pdf">language manual
        for North Sámi.</a> The Manual covers mainly how the voices will
        read certain constructions, but chapter 6 and 7 describes how to
        add your own pronunciations and words.</p>

        <section>
            <title>Institutional licenses</title>
            <p><a href="mailto:feedback@divvun.no">Contact Divvun</a> if
            you need licenses for many users at once, e.g. for a whole
            company or institution. If you want to install the voices on a
            server with TTS serivces, please contact Acapela (contact info
            below).</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>For developers</title>

            <p>The North Sámi text-to-speech system is available in several
            versions targeted at developers and others who want to integrate
            the synthesis in specific applications and systems:</p>

            <ul>
              <li>SDK: Acapela TTS for Windows – PC    </li>
              <li>SDK: Acapela TTS for Windows – Server</li>
              <li>SDK: Acapela TTS for Linux – Server  </li>
              <li>SDK: Acapela TTS for OS X        </li>
            </ul>

            <p>The SDK versions must be ordered directly from Acapela. Get in
            touch with Susanne Magnusson (<a
            href="mailto:susanne.magnusson@acapela-group.com"
            >susanne.magnusson@acapela-group.com</a>, tlf +46 8 799 86 02) for
            questions related to these versions.</p>

        </section>

   </body>
</document>
