<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
	<header>
		<title>Divvun spelling checkers for LibreOffice 4 on Windows 8</title>
	</header>

	<body>

			<p>The Divvun group has in cooperation with the <a
			href="http://voikko.puimula.org">Voikko</a> project and the <a
			href="http://hfst.sourceforge.net">Hfst</a> team developed a new
			serie of spelling checkers for LibreOffice. All source code for the
			spelling checkers is completely open, both the linguistic and the
			technical. In the long run this spelling checker will be integrated
			into other systems and applications.</p>

		<section>
			<title>Install the spellchecker</title>
			
			<warning>The spelling checkers for <a
			href="http://libreoffice.org/">LibreOffice</a> are still
			<strong>BETA</strong> quality. We appreciate all and any <a
			href="mailto:feedback@divvun.no">feedback</a>!</warning>

			<note>
				These installation instructions are written for the Divvun
				spelling checkers produced with Voikko and Hfst for
				<em>LibreOffice.org 4.1+</em>. There is a separate <a
				href="../mac/install-OOo-3.html">installation instruction for
				Divvun built for Hunspell</a> when used with
				LibreOffice 3.x and OpenOffice.org 2.x.
			</note>
			
			<p>Sami (and other) spelling checkers for LibreOffice can be
			downloaded <a href="/libreofficeoxt.html">here</a>. The downloaded
			spellchecker extension looks like this (the name may vary):<br/>
			<img src="images/win8-voikkooxt-fi-se-nn.png"
			alt="Bilde av LibreOffice-voikko-tillegget"/></p>

			<p>Depending on your browser and system, the downloaded file will
			either be automatically opened by LibreOffice or saved to disk.
			If it is saved, double click it to install the extension.</p>

            <p>LibreOffice will start and install the spelling checker. You will
            get a question whether you want to install it. Click «Ok» to
            install it:<br/>
            <img src="images/win8-installoxt-ok-nn.png"
            alt="Dialog for å sjekke om man vil installere tillegget."/></p>

            <p>When it is installed, a window like the one below will show up.
            In the picture below, the new speller extension is selected and
            highlighted in blue. You can click on the button "Innstillingar …"
            to see what languages are available in the speller.
            Click «Lukk» to end the installation.
            <br /><img src="images/win8-oxt-installert-nn.png"
            alt="Resultatet av installasjonen." /></p>

		</section>

		<section>
            <title>How to use the spelling checker</title>
            
            <note label="Windows users">If the input method and language are
            <a href="enable_sme_input-win8-nob.html">configured as
            recommended</a> in Windows 8.1, the spell checker language will
            follow the keyboard (input) language automatically. If so, the
            instructions below are superfluous. Just switch input method:
            English keyboard layout when writing in English, North Sámi keyboard
            when writing in North Sámi, etc. The speller language will switch
            together with the keyboard layout!</note>
            
            <p>To turn on the Divvn spell checker for North Sámi, do as follows:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Click the fourth field from the left in the status bar, and
                    then click «More …»: <br/>
    			 <img src="images/win8-LO4-switch-language-nn.png"
    			      alt="Språkmeny" /></li>
	       		<li>Choose the <strong>Font</strong> tab in the dialog window
	       		and choose the language you want (North Sámi in our case) from
	       		the popup <strong>language menu</strong>: <br/>
	       		 <img src="images/win8-LO4-select-language-nn.png"
	       		      alt="Skriftdialog" /></li>
			    <li>Now you can <strong>right click</strong> the misspelled word
			    and get correction suggestions (the "word" <em>nuvviDspeller</em>
			    will generate suggestions telling you what version you have of
			    the Divvun spell checker):<br />
			     <img src="images/win8-speller-popup-nn.png"
			     alt="Velg språk for stavekontroll" /></li>
            </ul>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
