<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
   <header>
      <title>Divvun info for administrators and integrators</title>
   </header>
   <body>
      <section>
         <title>Windows</title>
         <p>The <a href="korrektur.html">regular Divvun 4.1+ installers</a> are
            exe files
            wrapping two MSI packages: one MSI package for 32-bit Windows, and
            another MSI package for 64-bit Windows. This wrapping is done to
            make one installation package that is easy to install. If wanted or
            needed, each bit-specific package can be downloaded and installed
            separately, they can then be distributed
            and installed just like any other MSI package (links point to newest
            available version):</p>
         <ul>
            <li class="Download"><a
              href="http://divvun.no/static_files/msis/Divvun-sme-latest-win32.msi"
              ><icon alt="Download" height="44" width="44"
              src="images/Crystal_Clear_app_download_manager.png" />
              North Sámi, 32bit Windows</a>
            </li>
            <li class="Download"><a
              href="http://divvun.no/static_files/msis/Divvun-sme-latest-win64.msi"
              ><icon alt="Download" height="44" width="44"
              src="images/Crystal_Clear_app_download_manager.png" />
              North Sámi, 64bit Windows</a>
            </li>
            <li class="Download"><a
              href="http://divvun.no/static_files/msis/Divvun-smj-latest-win32.msi"
              ><icon alt="Download" height="44" width="44"
              src="images/Crystal_Clear_app_download_manager.png" />
              Julev Sámi, 32bit Windows</a>
            </li>
            <li class="Download"><a
              href="http://divvun.no/static_files/msis/Divvun-smj-latest-win64.msi"
              ><icon alt="Download" height="44" width="44"
              src="images/Crystal_Clear_app_download_manager.png" />
              Julev Sámi, 64bit Windows</a>
            </li>
            <li class="Download"><a
              href="http://divvun.no/static_files/msis/Divvun-sma-latest-win32.msi"
              ><icon alt="Download" height="44" width="44"
              src="images/Crystal_Clear_app_download_manager.png" />
              South Sámi, 32bit Windows</a>
            </li>
            <li class="Download"><a
              href="http://divvun.no/static_files/msis/Divvun-sma-latest-win64.msi"
              ><icon alt="Download" height="44" width="44"
              src="images/Crystal_Clear_app_download_manager.png" />
              South Sámi, 64bit Windows</a>
            </li>
         </ul>
         <p>To get at individual packages for all versions since 4.0.1, have a
         look at <a href="https://apertium.projectjj.com/spellers/release/">this
         page</a> (4.0 had a serious bug and is not available anymore).</p>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>MacOS X</title>
         <p>The Mac installer is made using Apple's own installer tools, and should be easily integratable in a larger
         deployment scheme. See Apple's own documentation for further details.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Old info related to the Windows 3.x-4.0.1 installers</title>
         <p>The Divvun 3.x and 4.0.1 installers are MSI packages, and can be distributed
            and installed just like any other MSI package.</p>
         <p>The Divvun 3.x tools do <strong>ONLY</strong> work with 32 bit Office,
            they do <strong>NOT</strong> work with 64 bit MS Office (but
            they work on both 32 and 64 bit Windows) (support for 64 bit Office
            was added in Divvun 4.0). If you have issues getting Divvun 3.x to
            work, please check that you have the 32 bit version of
            MS Office. Check <a
            href="http://www.addintools.com/documents/word/where-about.html">this
            page</a> for instructions on how to identify the bit-ness of your MS
            Office package.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Old info relating to the Divvun 2.x installer: Issues with Windows 7</title>
         <p>The Divvun 2.2 installer is made using NSIS, and is by default enabled for silent installations, and thus
         easy mass-deployment. You should run the installer using option <code>/S</code> to run it in silent mode:</p>
         <source>MSOfficeDivvunTools.exe /S</source>

         <p>Further info can be found in the <a href="http://nsis.sourceforge.net/Docs/Chapter4.html#4.12">NSIS
         documentation</a>, and the source code for building the installer can be found <a
         href="https://victorio.uit.no/langtech/trunk/prooftools/installers/win/MSOffice/nsis/source/">here</a>. If you
         have patches for bug fixes or feature enhancement, either <a href="mailto:feedback@divvun.no">send it via
         e-mail</a> or attach it to a <a href="http://giellatekno.uit.no/bugzilla/">Bugzilla bug</a>.</p>

         <p>Microsoft has changed several important (to us) aspects of the registry on Windows 7, which has caused
         (and is still causing) issues for the Divvun installer. For some of the issues there are workarounds, for
         others we are working on an updated installer. Known issues:</p>
         <dl>
            <dt>The Divvun tools are installed by a central administrator, but do not work for the local user:</dt>
            <dd><ul>
                  <li><strong>Cause:</strong> Windows7 only allows the registry entries to be set for the installing
                  user, which in this case is different from the actual end user</li>
                  <li><strong>Temporary solution:</strong> download and double-click one of the following registry
                  files, depending on your MS Office version:<ul>
                        <li><a
                        href="https://victorio.uit.no/langtech/trunk/prooftools/installers/win/MSOffice/nsis/source/divvun22-W7-O2007.reg">Divvun
                        2.2 registry file for Office 2007</a></li>
                        <li><a
                        href="https://victorio.uit.no/langtech/trunk/prooftools/installers/win/MSOffice/nsis/source/divvun22-W7-O2010.reg">Divvun
                        2.2 registry file for Office 2010</a></li>
                     </ul></li>
                  <li><strong>IMPORTANT:</strong> you need to double click the registry file <em>while you are logged
                  in as the user who is going to use the Divvun tools</em>. If the computer has more than one user,
                  you need to double click the registry file <em>once for each user</em>. This is a one time
                  operation for each user, after which Divvun should work as expected.</li>
                  <li><strong>WARNING:</strong> registry files can easily be used to compromise your Windows
                  computer. Make sure that the registry file you download is not tampered with or otherwise changed
                  by third parties. This can be done using an <strong>MD5</strong> checksum utility (here is <a
                  href="http://www.winmd5.com">a free MD5 checksum tool for Windows</a>). After you have downloaded
                  the registry files, drop them on the MD5 checksum tool, and control that you get <em>exactly</em>
                  the same checksum as given below. The checksums are:<ul>
                        <li>MD5 checksum for the Divvun 2.2 registry file for <strong>Windows7+Office 2007</strong>:
                        <code>df5d376b3cf2bf0063a0e0262219d225</code></li>
                        <li>MD5 checksum for the Divvun 2.2 registry file for <strong>Windows7+Office 2010</strong>:
                        <code>754bdd1767afde1489e6afc3fac69001</code></li>
                     </ul></li>
               </ul></dd>
            <dt>The Divvun tools are installed by the local user, but they still do not work:</dt>
            <dd><ul>
                  <li><strong>Cause:</strong> You have Office 2010 Home OR Student edition. These are not presently
                  supported.</li>
                  <li><strong>Temporary solution:</strong> None really. Upgrade to Officd 2010 Professional is a
                  solution, but will cost you money. A free solution is to use OpenOffice or LibreOffice, and install
                  our Hunspell speller.</li>
               </ul></dd>
         </dl>
      </section>

   </body>
</document>
