<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<document>
    <header>
        <title>First South Sámi Linguistic Days (SMA-BIEJJIEH)</title>
    </header>

    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Call for Papers</title>

            <p>2019 is the UN International Year of Indigenous Languages (IYIL).
            As part of IYIL, UiT The Arctic University of Norway and Nord
            University organise the first South Sámi Linguistic Days
            (SMA-BIEJJIEH) in Levanger, October 2-4, 2019.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Topics</title>
            <p>We invite researchers, students and language workers to submit
            papers on everything shedding new light on South Sámi grammar,
            especially concerning, but not restricted to:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>syntax</li>
                <li>synchronic and diachronic phonology</li>
                <li>morphology</li>
                <li>lexikografy</li>
                <li>dialectology</li>
                <li>phonetics</li>
                <li>language technology</li>
                <li>language history</li>
            </ul>

            <p>Abstrakts and final papers will receive doubleblind peer review,
            and
            all accepted papers will be published in a special issue of Nordlyd,
            Tromsø University Working Papers on Language &amp; Linguistics.
            Nordlyd is registered in The Norwegian Register for Scientific
            Journals, Series and Publishers.
            </p>

            <p>Nordlyd requires that authors be invited. All interested parties
            are hereby invited, and those getting their abstract accepted
            will be invited to submit an article.
            Abstracts can be sent by e-mail to
            <link href="mailto:divvun@uit.no">divvun@uit.no</link>. Please mark
            the e-mail <strong>SMA-BIEJJIEH</strong> in the subject line.
            </p>

            <p>We ask that submitted abstracts and papers follow the Nordlyd
            templates. There are templates for MS Word and LaTeX. We also ask
            that articles are limited to 20 pages, although exceptions can be
            made on requests. Please note that presentation time on
            the conference is restricted to 20 minutes + nine minutes for
            questions. Detailed information on templates and other guidelines
            will be given via e-mail, see above.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Invited speakers</title>

            <p>The following persons have been asked and have accepted to give a
            presentation:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>Lene Antonsen: «Maskinoversetting fra nordsamisk, bra eller
                dårlig for sørsamisk?»</li>
                <li>Eino Koponen: «Den sydsamiska ordlistan av Z. Plantinus ur
                ordbildningsmorfologisk synpunkt»</li>
                <li>David Kroik: (tittel blir annonsert senere)</li>
                <li>Ove Lorentz: (tittel blir annonsert senere)</li>
                <li>Bruce Morén-Duolja: (tittel blir annonsert senere)</li>
                <li>Trond Trosterud: «Partiklar i sørsamisk»</li>
                <li>Mikael Vinka: «Sydsamiska pronomen»</li>
                <li>Jussi Ylikoski: «Åarjelsaemien gïele goh dïhte jillemes
                Uralsken gïele» («Sørsamisk som det vestligste uralske
                språket»)</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Important dates</title>

            <ul>
                <li>19.8.2019: deadline for submitting abstract
                (max 2 pages + references)</li>
                <li>16.9.2019: reply to authors</li>
                <li>16.9.2019: conference registration deadline</li>
                <li>2.-4.10.2019: the conference</li>
                <li>1.11.2019: deadline for submitting final version of the
                paper</li>
            </ul>

            <p>Information on conference registration will be announced
            later.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Conference languages</title>

            <p>South Sámi and Scandinavian. The conference will be
            interpreted.</p>

            <p>The articles to be published in Nordlyd should have a summary in
            the other language (summary in South Sami if written in Scandinavian
            and the other way around) in addition to a summary in English.
            The editorial board can assist with the translation of summaries
            into South Sámi if needed.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Scientific committee</title>

            <ul>
                <li>Lene Antonsen</li>
                <li>Eino Koponen</li>
                <li>Michael Rießler</li>
                <li>Trond Trosterud</li>
                <li>Mikael Vinka</li>
                <li>Jussi Ylikoski</li>
            </ul>

            <p>Editorial board: Maja Lisa Kappfjell and Sjur Moshagen.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>